Statements like “beauty is in the eye of the beholder” are rarely questioned.
“美在观看者眼中”这类说法很少有人质疑。
They’ve become so embedded in our consciousness that people think it’s absurd to think otherwise.
这类说法已经深深植根于我们的意识之中，以至于人们认为持不同看法是荒谬的。
It might be useful, however, to at least push back on this assumption because people evaluate environments, situations, and people aesthetically.
不过，至少对这一假定提出异议或许是有益的，因为人们会从审美角度评价环境、情境和人。
We may find that we still believe it is correct, but we may also find that there is a lot more to the situation than we suppose.
我们可能会发现自己仍然认为这一假定是正确的，但也可能发现，情况远不像我们设想的那么简单。
A recent study exploring aesthetic taste was published in Cognition.
《认知》杂志最近发表了一项探究审美趣味的研究。
The results from this study show that people agree very much in their aesthetic evaluation of natural objects, but they disagree more about artifacts, or human-made objects.
这项研究的结果表明，人们对自然物体的审美评价非常一致，但在人工制品（即人造物品）上分歧更大。
The study found that shared taste was most common for faces and natural landscapes, but least common among works of architecture and art.
这项研究发现，共同的审美趣味在面孔和自然风景方面最为常见，而在建筑和艺术作品方面则最为少见。
The hypothesis is that the commonly pleasing features, like proportion or symmetry, are at work.
对此的假设是，比例或对称之类普遍令人愉悦的特征在起作用。
Preferences for natural scenes might be learned through life experiences.
对自然景色的偏好可能是通过生活经历习得的。
Factors like habitability, safety, and openness might be preferred as people develop.
人们在成长过程中可能会偏爱宜居性、安全性和开阔性之类的因素。
Some of the details of landscapes change, but the basics are more common, e.g., water, open spaces, and signs of care.
风景的某些细节会有所变化，但基本要素更为普遍，比如水、开阔的空间以及有人照料的迹象。
Art and architecture, unlike natural spaces, do not have the same level of exposure.
艺术和建筑与自然空间不同，人们接触它们的程度没有那么高。
So, people do not have the same level of shared taste.
所以，人们也就没有同样多的共同审美趣味。
It’s possible that the lower amount of agreement in the shared taste of artifacts has more to do with elements of style than with “behavioral consequences”.
在人工制品的共同审美趣味上，人们的一致程度较低，这可能更多地与风格要素有关，而不是与“行为后果”有关。
All of the consequences seem reasonable (or at least possible), but I think there might be an interesting philosophical conclusion that they did not draw.
所有这些推论似乎都合理（或者至少是可能成立的），但我认为，或许还有一个有趣的哲学结论，是研究者没有得出的。
It seems that there is an objective ground to our aesthetic preferences or evaluations.
看来，我们的审美偏好或审美评价有客观依据。
I am not saying this would mean beauty is completely objective, just that there could possibly be general objective principles at work, i.e., beauty is not simply in the eye of the beholder.
我并不是说这就意味着美是完全客观的，只是说有可能存在一些普遍的客观原则在起作用，也就是说，美并不只在观看者眼中。
Nature exhibits some of the universal aesthetic features, such as radiance, in a common way throughout the world.
大自然在世界各地以共通的方式展现出某些普遍的审美特征，比如光彩。
It’s not exactly the same everywhere, but it is common.
它并非在每个地方都一模一样，但却是共通的。
For example, a sunset is similar enough in different places to warrant almost universal appeal.
例如，不同地方的日落相似到足以使其具有近乎普遍的吸引力。
Possible universal principles of beauty—such as proportion, fittingness, radiance, and others—are general categories, which allow for a wide array of embodiments.
美可能具有的普遍原则——比如比例、适切、光彩等——都是宽泛的类别，容许各种各样的具体体现。
When people get involved in making artifacts in architecture or art, they apply these very general concepts in unique ways.
人们在建筑或艺术领域参与制作人工制品时，会以独特的方式运用这些非常宽泛的概念。
But the way they apply the principles may not have universal appeal.
但他们运用这些原则的方式可能并不具有普遍吸引力。
This is why it’s important to experience diverse cultures and their artifacts: doing so opens us up to different ways of approaching or constructing beauty.
正因如此，体验多元文化及其人工制品才很重要：这样做能让我们接触到看待或构建美的不同方式。
And it is always good to question our assumptions.
而且，对我们的假定提出质疑总是有益的。